Vishant Bhat

SAS | Data Management | Business Intelligence | Big Data | Hadoop

Summary

I have more than 10 years of experience in helping organisation with strategy and implementation of Business Intelligence, Data warehousing and Big Data solution implementation with technologies best fitting the organisation and business needs.

Extensive experience in programs to collect, store, analyse and visualize data from various sources for specific projects to achieve the goals, while ensuring the quality and on-time delivery according to the specifications.I am able to develop big data solution recommendations and ensure implementation of the chosen big data solution on premises or Cloud.

Familiarity with disciplines like text mining, clustering analysis, recommendation analysis, outlier detection, predictive analytics or similarity searches as well as different modelling techniques.

I am able to communicate effectively at executive level with executive management when advising an organisation and to improve business results using big data technology to translate business issues into big data solutions that will help (senior) managers in their decision-making.

Project execution: SDLC - Waterfall Model and Iterative Models, Agile and Scrum methods.

HADOOP ecosystem - HDFS, Pig, Hive, HBase, Sqoop, Oozie, HUE (Hadoop User Interface)

SAS Skills - SAS Base/Macro/SQL, Data Integration Studio, Web Report Studio, Information Maps, Cube Studio, Enterprise Guide, Visual Analytics and Platform Computing for scheduling

Databases - Teradata, Oracle, MySQL, SQL Server and MS Access

Operating Systems - Windows, Linux (Fedora, CentOS, RHEL), Unix, Ubuntu

Data Quality Tools: SAS Dataflux

Data Model Tool: CA Erwin, Oracle SQL Developer, Innovator MID

Other Tools: GIT, JIRA, Conflunce, SVN

Page1

Experience

Data Modeler at University of Newcastle (UON), Australia

April 2015 - Present (1 year 3 months)

The Strategy, Planning and Performance (SPP) unit of the University of Newcastle (UON) facilitates continuous improvement and effective data-driven decision-making across UON. The team coordinates integrated planning processes that support the University to achieve its strategic objectives and leads a range of quality assurance activities. SPP delivers institutional performance data through the Management Information System (MIS) and Newcastle Information and Analytics (NINA) Visual Analytics portal.

Technical Consultant at Professional Services - SAS R&D

January 2013 - March 2015 (2 years 3 months)

SAS is the leader in analytics. Through innovative analytics, business intelligence and data management software and services, SAS helps customers at more than 80,000 sites make better decisions faster. Since 1976, SAS has been giving customers around the world THE POWER TO KNOW®

The SAS R& D center center in India is the first R&D center outside the US. Its Professional Services arm provides,

- 1. Consulting, Services including solution development and implementation.
- 2. Project Management and closeout at customer sites.
- 3. Assisting pre-sales and sales teams with enablement activities and ensure the highest levels of customer satisfaction.

IT Consultant at Tech Mahindra (formerly Mahindra Satyam)

February 2012 - January 2013 (1 year)

A leading global information, communications and technology (ICT) company, part of the US \$14.4 billion Mahindra Group, a global industrial federation of companies and one of the top 10 business houses based in India. Mahindra Satyam is powered by a pool of talented IT and consulting professionals across enterprise solutions, client relationship management, business intelligence, business process quality, operations management, engineering solutions, digital convergence, product lifecycle management, and infrastructure management services, among other capabilities.

IT Analyst at Tata Consultancy Services

July 2006 - February 2012 (5 years 8 months)

A software services and consulting company headquartered in Mumbai, India. TCS is the largest provider of information technology and business process outsourcing services in India. TCS is a flagship subsidiary of one of India's largest and oldest company, the Tata Group, which has interests in areas such as energy, telecommunications, financial services, manufacturing, chemicals, engineering, materials, government and healthcare.

Projects

Hadoop Ecosystem: Processing BigData in Real-Time, Near Real-time and Batch

April 2014 to Present

Members: Vishant Bhat

This is one of my ongoing projects to get started with hadoop and implement a complete Data Warehousing and Business Intelligence Use Case on top of the ecosystem. I am starting off with a 10Gb data of logs file from Quorora and Wiki databases. My cluster is a 2 node Mac OS X and Linux machine system.

I have installed and configured the below ecosystem components

- 1. Hadoop HDFS storage and YARN for Map-Reduce processing.
- 2. HIVE SQL for large-scale processing of ETL jobs in Map-Reduce mode.
- 3. PIG For small data processing and quick analysis and query the data in warehouse.
- 4. HCatalog Metadata Platform for all Hadoop ecosystem components viz. PIG, HIVE.
- 5. HBase Quick random, real time read/write access to cluster data.
- 6. SQOOP High speed bulk data transfer between RDBMS and HDFS file systems.
- 7. OOZIE Scheduling and Workflow manager for Hadoop ecosystem component jobs.
- 8. MySQL as a backend Meta store for storing metadata (used in place of Derby default) related to Jobs, Queries and workflows.
- 9. HUE User Interface for all the ecosystem components
- 10. Solr Search and Dashboard for Real-time and on-the-fly Analytics and Visualization

Currently the cluster is operational and running jobs on schedule for performing custom ETL for transforming and loading data from Flat files (from various log files) to RDBMS tables. I have done performance tuning for Map-Reduce jobs so that whenever a job is submitted i.e. Adhoc querying or scheduled job flow the jobs runs faster.

IMPORTANT - Packaging the whole ecosystem to "run and install" with a "single command" so that we have "Ease of install" and "maintainability" for any Admin on any flavour of Linux/Unix. I am trying to achieve by "GIT Hub"

Next Steps:-

- 1. Adding Real-time streaming data support
- 2. Analysis of Data using R-packages
- 3. Packaging

The Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Co.

December 2012 to September 2013

Members: Vishant Bhat, Bhushan Kaple, Ravikiran Bhyri

Implement a custom-built SAS solution for creation of 3 On-demand actions, to be used by the A&P business users to create and validate promotions. This is a Promotion Price Optimization solution which runs in the back end to aid in the promotions creation and execution cycle.

Worked on Revenue Optimization (RO) architecture which had GRID computing for workload balancing and parallel processing.

SAS Tools: SAS Base/Macro/SQL, SAS Merchandise Intelligence

One of USA's largest Pharma company

August 2013 to January 2015

Members: Vishant Bhat, Ravikiran Bhyri

Implement a custom-built, SAS-based solution called the Contract Effectiveness System (CES). SAS determined that the underlying data processing code and tables needed to be re-architected and re-designed for CESV4 to leverage the suite of data loading and quality tools within SAS Data Management Standard offering.

As part of the SAS consulting team we were to build new ETLs and quality controls to load the data into a new, streamlined data table design known as the Uniform Data Structure (UDS).

SAS Tools: SAS Base/Macro/SQL, SAS Data Integration Studio

USA's largest Non-profit Healthcare Organization

October 2014 to April 2015

Members: Vishant Bhat, "Viru" paxi Mirje, YOGESH SINGH, Carrie Boorse

Client and SAS Institute, Inc. have established the terms for a win-win, multi-year partnership to develop a healthcare-optimized, enterprise Analytic's platform, upon which will be incubated an increasingly comprehensive suite of high-value, differentiated, advanced analytic offerings that will be consumed both by the client and SAS, over time, by the broader health care market. This collection of offerings will be deployed to client. This is for the first time that real-time and analytical processing is done using Hadoop Ecosystem supported by SAS Technology stack.

Forecasting and Order Planning, TESCO UK

February 2012 to January 2013

Members: Vishant Bhat, Sunpreet Singh, Pankaj Revankar

The objectives of the F&OP project are to design and deliver a solution (business process, organisation and systems) that will enhance the capability of the Non-Food business to:

- Develop an automated demand and supply planning solution to manage an increased SKU count using the same or fewer resources.
- Predict customer demand with greater accuracy to inform business planning decisions throughout the product life cycle (from long-range forecasting to support season planning to SKU-store level forecasting to support replenishment planning)
- Plan supplier to DC orders taking into account relevant demand forecasts, safety stock policies and appropriate supply chain parameters

SAS Tools: SAS Base/Macro/SQL, SAS Data Integration Studio, SAS Business Intelligence Tools

Allianz Global Data warehouse and Reporting

August 2011 to January 2012

Members: Vishant Bhat, Koteswararao Gunji, "Viru" paxi Mirje

The Project is a migration of data and reports from a Business Objects based system BOXI to SAS BI. Allianz Re decided in 2009 to review their systems and migrate their reporting from BOXI. SAS was chosen as the leading player for this along with Technology and Services partner TCS. The data was moved in a phased manner to SAS using SAS DI and current resides in SAS DI v4.2 installed on UNIX Server.

Retirement Control & Valuation

November 2010 to June 2011

Members: Vishant Bhat, Daniel Harding

The project involved building a SAS based tool for system redesign and verification for the Retirement Control policies and valuation methodology. The Project was broken down into the 5 parts with modules being developed at each stage of completion and executed independently.

- Data Analysis and Correction
- Valuation System Redesign
- Indexation Issues
- Partial Fractions

SAS Tools: SAS Base/Macro/SQL, SAS Data Integration Studio, SAS Business Intelligence

Operations Center India & Query Management System

October 2008 to November 2010

Members: Vishant Bhat

The Query Management System (QMS) is a Data warehousing system built for Global Credit Control (GCC) and corporate finance of XL. Every scanned invoice and the related queries arising from the scan are tracked and closed in the QMS. The QMS system is designed and developed in SAS platform. Its basic functionality includes Creation/Deletion of QMS scan user profiles, Reporting, Load Monitoring, Query Tracking/Editing and Administration.

One of USA's largest Pharmacuetical company

September 2006 to September 2008

Members: Vishant Bhat, Aparna Agrawal

The Project involved providing Global Medical Regulatory – IT Support (GMR-IT) for the client. The team comprised of 800+ associates providing end-to-end IT support, for aiding the client in submission of Drug Related Information, reports, DB's to the Federal Drug Agency(FDA), this was part of the Clinical Trial Process, where a molecule is discovered, separated for study, tried on Patients and bought to marked with proper approvals at each stage from the FDA.

A dedicated SAS team comprising of 120 people, involving Statisticians and programmers were aiding in Reporting and Database preparation in SAS using Mainframes

Hadoop Enablement for PSCC

April 2014 to April 2015

Members: Vishant Bhat, Bhushan Kaple, Maireen Kaur

As part of PSCC Hadoop enablement team, we were tasked with setting up of a hadoop cluster for SAS Hadoop activities. This included,

- 1. Setting up of Hadoop Cluster in PSCC SRDI
- 2. Managing Cluster
- 3. Administration
- 4. Case Study implementation

We successfully setup the cluster with HDFS, HIVE, PIG ecosystem components on RHEL 6 on 4 Virtual Machine Servers. The cluster will act as a base for further testing, development and enablement activities for any consulting or PoC or PoV in PSCC SRDI.

Languages

English(Full professional proficiency)Kannada(Native or bilingual proficiency)Hindi(Native or bilingual proficiency)Marathi(Native or bilingual proficiency)Konkani(Native or bilingual proficiency)

Honors and Awards

On the Spot Award

Tata Consultancy Services

October 2008

3 Times On the Spot Award for going beyond scope of work to get the job done for SAS Implementation Projects

Service & Commitment Award

Tata Consultancy Services

July 2011

Long Term Service and Commitment Award for completing 5 years in Tata Consultancy Services.

Skills & Expertise

SAS

Data Warehousing

ETL

Unix

Business Intelligence

Analysis

Oracle

Data Modeling

Testing

SQL

PL/SQL

Business Analytics

Business Analysis

Data Integration

SDLC

SAS Base/Macro/SQL

Analytics

Requirements Gathering

Informatica

DB₂

Requirements Analysis

SAS Data Integration/ETL

SAS Business Intelligence

Retail Banking

Credit Card Transaction Processing

Hadoop

Hive

Big Data

Consulting

Management

Databases

Data Management

Data Analysis

Data Quality

Enterprise Software

Agile Methodologies

Certifications

Certified in Basics of Banking

Indian Institute of Banking and Finance- IIBF October 2014

Certified in Operations of Credit Cards Business

Indian Institute of Banking and Finance- IIBF January 2015

SAS Certified Base Programmer for SAS 9

SAS November 2012

SAS Certified Advanced Programmer for SAS 9

SAS June 2014

SAS Certified Data Integration Developer for SAS 9

SAS December 2013

SAS Certified Platform Administrator for SAS 9

SAS March 2014

Education

Visvesvaraya Technological University

Bachelor of Engineering (BE), Computer Science, 2002 - 2006

Grade: First Class

Activities and Societies: 1. Treasurer for Association of Computer Science and Engineering (ACES). 2. Organized and Conducted State-Level Engineering Festival. 3. Quiz Master and Anchor for IT Quiz as part of

the Tech Fest.

Karnatak University

High School, Science - Physics/Chemistry/Mathematics/Biology, 2000 - 2002

Grade: First Class

Basel Mission English Medium School

Secondary School, 1990 - 2000

Grade: First Class

Publications

Running SAS MI Solution in Parallel for Revenue Optimization

SAS Tech Expo - SAS R&D India Pvt Ltd June 2013

Authors: Vishant Bhat, Bhushan Kaple

What was done?

Improve the promotion plans processing performance of SAS Promotion Plan optimization (PPO) 5.2 M2 to an acceptable threshold.

Problem Solved:

- Process large number of promotion plans over the weekday (~1000 plans) and weekend (~12000-16000)
- Load data in a limited loading window of 8 hours for a weekday and 24 hours for a weekend
- SLA system to be available to the business users by 7.00 AM EST on a business day.

Processing CDC and SCD Type-2 for Sources Without CDC- Hybrid Approach

SAS Global Forum 2016 January 31, 2016

Authors: Vishant Bhat

In a data warehousing system Change Data capture (CDC) plays an important role not just in making the data warehouse (DWH) aware of the change but also providing a means of flowing the change to the DWH marts and reporting tables so that we see the current and latest version of the truth. This together with Slowly Changing Dimensions (SCD) create a cycle which runs the DWH and provides valuable insights in the history and decision making future when used by machine learning, pattern recognition and forecasting methods. What if the source has no CDC? It would be an ETL nightmare to identify the exact change and report the absolute truth. This hybrid approach shows how to increase the data and metadata capture and quality in data warehouses. Application of this hybrid approach can provide information that is otherwise hidden in areas such as Audit and Fraud detection, while the efficiency provides opportunities for rapidly changing dimensions.

Vishant Bhat

SAS | Data Management | Business Intelligence | Big Data | Hadoop



2 person has recommended Vishant

"High level of ownership is the phrase that comes to mind when I think about Vishant. I've had the pleasure of knowing Vishant for two years during which he was with SAS R&D Pune as part of my consulting team. Above all, I was impressed with Vishant's ability to own and successfully deliver any assignments big or small. And, of course, his/her personal drive to constantly learn and coach other members of the team. Vishant would be a true asset for any positions requiring any competency in Data & Big Data management and comes with my heartfelt recommendation."

— **Mukund Wadekar**, *Director - Services*, *SAS Corp*, managed Vishant indirectly at Professional Services - SAS R&D

"I've had the privilege of working with Vishant for little more than 2 years in SAS and in that time I have known Vishant as go to person for any SAS queries, be it programming or any solution. He is a pragmatic leader and always open to new challenges while keeping attention to details. He is not just technical expert but also understands the business very well, this makes him value creator in the truest sense."

— **Kunal Kelkar**, *Analytical Consultant*, *SAS R&D India Pvt. Ltd.*, worked directly with Vishant at Professional Services - SAS R&D

Contact Vishant on LinkedIn